<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The perfect man described in his life and end In a funeral discourse upon Psalm XXXVII. 37. Occasioned by the death of that pattern of uprightness Mr. Edward Lawrence. By Nathanael Vincent, M.A. minister of the Gospel. Whereunto are added some passages out of two letters, written by two excellent ministers concerning Mr. Lawrence; who were well acquainted with him, and with the worth of him.</title>
            <author>Vincent, Nathanael, 1639?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64967</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V416</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218124</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829746</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829746</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34189</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64967)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34189)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2002:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The perfect man described in his life and end In a funeral discourse upon Psalm XXXVII. 37. Occasioned by the death of that pattern of uprightness Mr. Edward Lawrence. By Nathanael Vincent, M.A. minister of the Gospel. Whereunto are added some passages out of two letters, written by two excellent ministers concerning Mr. Lawrence; who were well acquainted with him, and with the worth of him.</title>
                  <author>Vincent, Nathanael, 1639?-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for B. Aylmer, at the Three Pigeons against the Royal Exchange, in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With preliminary half title reading: Mr. Vincent's funeral discourse occasioned by the death of Mr. Edward Lawrence.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A funeral sermon.</note>
                  <note>"Several passages concerning Mr. Lawrence, out of two letters" has caption title on p. 22.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement at foot on final page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Congregational Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lawrence, Edward, 1623-1695 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms, XXXVII, 37 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34189:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34189:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Perfect Man deſcribed in his Life and End.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN A <hi>Funeral Diſcourſe</hi> Upon <hi>Pſalm</hi> XXXVII. 37.</p>
            <p>Occaſioned by the DEATH Of that <hi>Pattern</hi> of <hi>Uprightneſs</hi> Mr. EDWARD LAWRENCE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nathanael Vincent,</hi> M. A. Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Whereunto are added ſome Paſſages out of <hi>Two Letters,</hi> written by <hi>Two Excellent Miniſters</hi> concerning Mr. <hi>Lawrence;</hi> who were well acquainted with him, and with the Worth of him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>B. Aylmer,</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:34189:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34189:2"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>VINCENT's Funeral Diſcourſe</hi> Occaſioned by the DEATH of Mr. <hi>EDWARD LAWRENCE.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34189:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34189:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:34189:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34189:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THAT CONGREGATION Who had Mr.</hi> EDWARD LAWRENCE <hi>For their PASTOR.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My much reſpected Friends!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen I preached <hi>this Sermon,</hi> which now I preſent <hi>eſpecially</hi> to <hi>you;</hi> I was ſo far from having the leaſt thought of Printing it, that I had not written ſo much as one word of it; and when your Deſires were expreſs'd that it might be Publiſh'd, I diſcovered a <hi>great averſeneſs,</hi> becauſe I knew how much averſe my deceaſed and <hi>moſt true Friend</hi> was from a Diſcourſe relating to Himſelf; and much more would he have been againſt the <hi>Printing</hi> any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Him. But your <hi>reitereated Deſires prevailed,</hi> being ſeconded by <hi>that Argument,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:34189:5"/> himſelf went contrary to the declared Will of an <hi>Eminent Chriſtian,</hi> in <hi>Preaching</hi> a <hi>Funeral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and giving him his <hi>deſerved Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> Adding, that becauſe that Excellent Saint was <hi>againſt</hi> his <hi>Preaching, therefore</hi> he was the <hi>more forward</hi> to do it. So that I have only made bold to <hi>mete the ſame Meaſure</hi> to my <hi>Friend</hi> who is <hi>dead and gone,</hi> which <hi>He</hi> did mete to his <hi>Friend</hi> that died before him.</p>
            <p>This Sermon for the Subſtance of it was taken from my Mouth in <hi>Short-hand,</hi> and brought to me written out in <hi>Long.</hi> And ſince you have importuned the making of it publick, I deſire you may give it a ſerious peruſal.</p>
            <p>A <hi>perfect Man</hi> is the moſt <hi>glorious</hi> and <hi>love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> of all <hi>viſible Creatures.</hi> How much of the <hi>Image of the inviſible God</hi> does <hi>ſhine forth</hi> in him! The Grace of God in Truth whereever <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>tis wrought, what a bleſſed Change does it make! Out of the <hi>rubbiſh and ruins</hi> of <hi>corrupt Nature,</hi> there is built an <hi>Holy Temple</hi> for the <hi>living God!</hi> And in this Temple how is <hi>He</hi> honoured and ſerved! The perfect Man hath an <hi>high Aim,</hi> and a <hi>commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Emulation;</hi> he deſires to <hi>do the will of God on earth, as it's done in heaven.</hi> And Heaven is eſteemed a bleſſed place, becauſe there he ſhall be able fully to do what he does deſire.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34189:5"/>
            <p> I have heard your <hi>deceaſed Paſtor</hi> expreſs his long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to be <hi>in an holy and happy Eternity.</hi> Tho he had <hi>many other Loads,</hi> Sin <hi>was his heavieſt Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then;</hi> and <hi>perfect Holineſs</hi> was look'd upon as a <hi>great part</hi> of his <hi>expected Bleſſedneſs.</hi> He was a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and a profitable Preacher; and this muſt be added, that he <hi>preached continually.</hi> His <hi>ſerious Looks,</hi> his <hi>edifying Communication, which adminiſtred Grace to the Hearers;</hi> his <hi>holy, juſt, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable and ſhining Converſation,</hi> were <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtructive;</hi> and by <hi>theſe</hi> he was <hi>ever ſpeaking</hi> to all that obſerved him, that it was much for <hi>their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> to be <hi>like</hi> him. And now <hi>being dead, he yet ſpeaks to</hi> you, <hi>that the Counſels</hi> he gave you, which are <hi>the Counſels of God,</hi> ſhould <hi>not dye with him,</hi> nor be <hi>buried in Oblivion.</hi> The <hi>Flock</hi> of <hi>ſuch a Paſtor</hi> ſhould be Eminent for Contempt of the World, ſerious Holineſs, and Heavenly-Mindedneſs, elſe they will be far from reſembling their Faithful Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hard.</p>
            <p>I cannot wiſh you better, than that the Lord would direct you to ſettle under a Miniſter <hi>moſt like him</hi> who is taken from you; and who will <hi>naturally care</hi> for your <hi>Spiritual Eſtate.</hi> I wiſh his <hi>Family</hi> may <hi>be cared for</hi> by that God, whom he ſerved in Truth and Sincerity, <hi>whoſe mercy is from everlaſting to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting upon them that fear him, and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:34189:6"/> 
               <hi>unto childrens children, to ſuch as keep his covenant, and remember his commandments to do them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Earth is <hi>emptying apace</hi> of them who are <hi>ripe for Heaven;</hi> I wiſh the <hi>Death</hi> of thoſe that are gone, may make both <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> that remain and ſurvive, to be <hi>more lively</hi> and diligent in their Lord's Work! The <hi>Time</hi> of <hi>Labour</hi> is ſhort; but <hi>to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> it will be <hi>found,</hi> that <hi>labour is not in vain in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Friends,</hi> I commend <hi>you</hi> and <hi>yours</hi> to the <hi>Great Shepherd of Souls,</hi> and <hi>to the Word of his Grace;</hi> and wiſh your <hi>Perfection</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> living, dying, and for ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant for Jeſus ſake, NATHANAEL VINCENT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34189:6"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSALM XXXVII. 37.</bibl>
               <q>Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright: for the end of that man is peace.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>ALTHO Liberty to Preach the Goſpel is juſtly eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the privilege and pleaſure of my Life; and tho a <hi>Regal Throne,</hi> or a <hi>Triple Crown,</hi> is to me contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible in compariſon of a <hi>Pulpit;</hi> yet I muſt needs confeſs that I come with a <hi>ſad heart</hi> to preach the Word this day; and the reaſon of my Sorrow is, the <hi>loſs</hi> of that <hi>Excellent Man</hi> and <hi>Miniſter of Chriſt,</hi> who dwelt in this place, who is now <hi>effectually ſilenced</hi> by Death, and muſt be <hi>heard to Preach no more for ever.</hi> This <hi>burning and ſhining Light,</hi> a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years ago, was <hi>put under a Buſhel,</hi> which was worthy to have been ſet in a Golden Candleſtick; but now alas! in a ſenſe 'tis quite extinguiſhed: He is <hi>gone into darkneſs and the ſhadow of Death, where there is no order, and where the light is as darkneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had in his life-time <hi>declared his Will</hi> againſt a <hi>Funeral Sermon;</hi> for he was far from affecting thoſe Praiſes and Commendations which are uſually given in Funeral Diſcourſes; but I muſt ſay, that the <hi>leſs he deſired,</hi> the <hi>more he deſerved</hi> to be praiſed and commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; having ſuch a <hi>large ſhare of Humility,</hi> joyned with his other <hi>great Miniſterial Accompliſhments.</hi> When the news of his Death came firſt to my ears, I ſaid what I thought, and had good ground to be perſwaded of: <hi>Now there is a Man gone out of the World, that was one of the beſt Men in it.</hi> Good Men may truly be called <hi>Pillars</hi> of the Earth; and when a <hi>very ſtrong Pillar</hi> is thrown down, there ſhould be <hi>great Lamentation;</hi> and the <hi>Earth may tremble</hi> at the <hi>fall</hi> of it. But tho he is gone down to the Duſt, where his Face is bound in ſecret, and muſt be ſeen no more, till this World be no more; yet <hi>methinks I have a view of him</hi> plainly in the <hi>Text</hi> I have choſen; here we have his <hi>Character</hi> both <hi>Living</hi> and <hi>Dying: Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright: for the end of that man is peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:34189:7"/>
            <p> In which words, I ſhall offer theſe particulars to your Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Here is a <hi>remarkable Man,</hi> and he is the <hi>perfect Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Wherein the <hi>perfection of this Man lies;</hi> it lies in his <hi>being upright.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> What the perfect and upright Man is <hi>worthy of;</hi> he is worthy to be <hi>marked,</hi> he is worthy to be <hi>beheld.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> What of this perfect and upright Man <hi>our eye in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner ſhould be upon,</hi> and that is <hi>his end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> His end is remarkable as well as himſelf, for his <hi>end is peace.</hi> An <hi>upright Life,</hi> and a <hi>peaceful Death,</hi> how <hi>truly deſirable</hi> are they! and the <hi>former</hi> is the <hi>way</hi> to the <hi>latter;</hi> whereas <hi>there is no peace, ſaith the Lord, to the wicked</hi> while he lives; and when he dies and his Soul is required at his hands, he will perceive how <hi>fooliſh</hi> he was, in <hi>crying peace and ſafety to himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Particulars</hi> I ſhall <hi>inſiſt</hi> on, and then conclude with the <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt place I am to ſpeak of the <hi>remarkable Man</hi> in the Text, and he is the <hi>perfect Man.</hi> It is a wonder, conſidering the general Corruption and Depravation of Humane Nature, and how full of Snares and Temptations this World is, that there <hi>ſhould be ever a perfect Man upon Earth!</hi> But ſee what the <hi>powerful Grace</hi> of God can do. It can <hi>renew and alter Nature it ſelf,</hi> and change it from <hi>contrary to contrary,</hi> from <hi>wickedneſs</hi> and <hi>deceitfulneſs,</hi> to <hi>holineſs of truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the perfect Man may be the better underſtood, you muſt know that there is a <hi>threefold Perfection</hi> ſpoken of in Scripture.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Legal.</item>
               <item>Coeleſtial.</item>
               <item>Evangelical.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. There is a <hi>Legal Perfection:</hi> This was in <hi>Adam before the Fall;</hi> he was made <hi>perfect and upright;</hi> but being made mutable, he quickly <hi>ſought out many inventions,</hi> Eccleſ. 7. 29. and made himſelf quite and clean another Creature from what he was at firſt created. When other things were made, God's bare word of command that they ſhould be, gave them a Being; but when Man was to be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34189:7"/> formed, it was not done without ſome kind of <hi>Solemnity and Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> Gen. 1. 26. <hi>And God ſaid, Let us make man in our image, after our likeneſs.</hi> And how did Man ſhine with this Image upon him, when he came firſt out of his Maker's hands! If all things were very good in their kind, how <hi>perfect</hi> was <hi>Man's Goodneſs</hi> in <hi>his kind!</hi> not the leaſt <hi>moral Evil</hi> was to be found in him. What a clear light was there in his mind! How exactly conformed was his Will to the Divine Will! How regular were his Affections! Not the leaſt Evil was in him, either in Action, Thought, or Inclination.</p>
            <p>He had a <hi>Power</hi> to keep the <hi>whole Law of God</hi> in every Part and Point of it, and a <hi>Will moſt free</hi> and forward in it. He could, and for a while did come up to the terms of the firſt Covenant, <hi>Do this and live.</hi> And thus perfect he did remain, till through the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the evil One, he let go his primitive Righteouſneſs and Integrity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a <hi>Coeleſtial Perfection,</hi> and that is the Perfection of <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified Saints in Heaven;</hi> we cannot aſpire unto, or deſire any thing for our ſelves, higher than, or ſo high as this. This the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, 1 Cor. 13. 9, 10. <hi>For we know in part, and we prophecy in part; but when that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part ſhall he done away.</hi> This Perfection is preached of, and heard of at preſent; and they who attain to the greateſt meaſure of Grace and Holineſs, can beſt give a gueſs at it: <hi>Our Brother,</hi> who is lately taken away from us, now <hi>underſtands</hi> and <hi>experiences to his Joy</hi> what <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens perfection</hi> is. We read, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 23. of the <hi>general Aſſembly and Church of the firſt-born which are written in Heaven, and the ſpirits of juſt Men made perfect.</hi> How clear is that light, in which <hi>God, who is light,</hi> is ſeen! How perfect is that Purity which is conſequent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Viſion of him! how have they all been transformed into the Image of him whom they do behold, fully reſembling him in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs! 1 John 3. 2. <hi>We know that when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeparated Spirits of Saints, having left their <hi>Earthly Houſe and Tabernacle,</hi> have put off their ſinful Infirmities; <hi>nothing</hi> that makes them in the <hi>leaſt unlike to God,</hi> or that <hi>he diſlikes,</hi> remains in them. The great Phyſician <hi>began the Cure</hi> of thoſe bleſſed Souls in <hi>this</hi> World, and now in the <hi>other World 'tis perfected;</hi> that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is applicable to every one of them, Cant. 4. 7. <hi>Thou art all fair my love, there is no ſpot in thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:34189:8"/>
            <p> And as the Spirits of juſt Men in Heaven are perfect; ſo their <hi>vile bodies will be changed and made like unto Chriſt's glorious body.</hi> Heb. 3. 21. this <hi>corruptible will put on incorruption, this mortal immortality. Adam</hi>'s Body before the Fall was of an <hi>admirable Make and Conſtitution,</hi> not the leaſt <hi>peccant Humour</hi> in it. And if he had ſtood, the <hi>Tree of Life,</hi> the Sacrament of the firſt Covenant, was to <hi>aſſure him of Immortality;</hi> yet that Body was <hi>much inferior</hi> to a <hi>Spiritual Body</hi> at the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Oh how <hi>illuſtriouſly perfect</hi> as to their <hi>whole Man,</hi> will all Saints be, when <hi>Chriſt their life ſhall appear, and they appear with him in glory!</hi> Col. 3 4. The <hi>perfection of Heaven,</hi> which <hi>Chriſt is the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſer of,</hi> will be found by many degrees to be <hi>beyond that Perfection</hi> which was in the <hi>firſt Paradice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. There is an <hi>Evangelical Perfection:</hi> and the Man ſpoken of in the Text, is in <hi>this Senſe</hi> perfect. Legal Rigour is abated in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; the Goſpel <hi>does not curſe</hi> every one that <hi>continues not in all things</hi> required in the Law. Legal exactneſs is not expected from Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; God does <hi>not mark iniquities,</hi> nor <hi>enter into judgment</hi> with them. A <hi>ſincere Saint is evangelically a perfect Man;</hi> tho in <hi>ſtrictneſs of Law,</hi> there is <hi>ſome Imperfection</hi> in his Holineſs. The Apoſtle, <hi>without Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contradiction,</hi> affirms himſelf to be <hi>perfect</hi> and <hi>not perfect,</hi> almoſt in the ſame breath Phil. 3. 12. <hi>Not as tho I had already attained, or were already perfect;</hi> and yet he ſays ver. 15. <hi>Let us therefore as many as be perfect be thus indeed.</hi> He had a perfection of ſincerity; but unto a ſinleſs perfection he had not attained.</p>
            <p>The Evangelically perfect Man, I am now to deſcribe.</p>
            <p>The perfect Man is <hi>renewed in all his Parts and Powers.</hi> The whole Man is corrupted by Nature, and the whole Man is renewed by Grace. This the Apoſtle expreſſes by <hi>Sanctification throughout, in body, ſoul, and ſpirit,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5. 23. Tho in degree, Sanctification be put in part; yet every part is truly and really ſanctified. When the Lord makes a perfect Man, he works a change in <hi>the whole Man.</hi> Nothing in the Soul but has <hi>ſome gracious Alteration</hi> wrought in it. <hi>No one Power or Faculty</hi> is let alone <hi>to be altogether as it was.</hi> The Mind is enlightned, the Conſcience awakened, the Will and Affections have a new byaſs; and the Memory retains things neceſſary and worthy to be remembred; and the <hi>heart being purified,</hi> the members are yielded as <hi>Inſtruments of Righteouſneſs unto Holineſs.</hi> The new Creature lacks not any parts, and degrees of Grace are ſtill to be added: In this Senſe <hi>all things are become new,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 17. and yet the <hi>inward man</hi> is further <hi>to be renewed day by day,</hi> 2 Cor. 4. 16.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:34189:8"/>
            <p> 2. The perfect Man is <hi>made pertaker of every Grace.</hi> Moral Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers have obſerved a Concatenation of all moral Virtues, that they are inſeparable; where <hi>one</hi> is indeed, there are all of them. There cannot be <hi>truly any Vertue</hi> in any man, where <hi>any one Vice</hi> is allowed to be <hi>predominant.</hi> 'Tis a great truth concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the Graces</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> that they are <hi>all linked together.</hi> There is <hi>no Grace inſincerity</hi> in that man, who <hi>ordinarily</hi> and <hi>preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly</hi> does what he knows to be evil in God's ſight, and <hi>willingly ſuffers,</hi> tho it be <hi>but one Iniquity</hi> to have <hi>the dominion over him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Spirit of God works like himſelf; and <hi>all Grace</hi> he works, where he <hi>works any.</hi> The Stone or Kernel of the Fruit tree, has <hi>vertually</hi> the <hi>whole Tree</hi> in it; and if it be ſown in the Ground, a Tree with Leaves and Fruit at length grows up from it. We read of the <hi>ſeed of God,</hi> 1 John 3. 9. and this Seed <hi>vertually has all Grace</hi> in it: And this Seed does <hi>remain;</hi> and Grace of <hi>every ſort,</hi> as there is occaſion, in ſome degree or other, is produced into act and exerciſe.</p>
            <p>In the perfect man's <hi>breaſt plate,</hi> or if you will in his <hi>breaſt,</hi> there is <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs:</hi> It is <hi>Hope</hi> that is his <hi>Helmet.</hi> It is <hi>Humility</hi> that is both his <hi>Cloathing</hi> and <hi>Ornament;</hi> and <hi>Zeal</hi> is not ſo much <hi>one ſingle Grace,</hi> as an <hi>high degree</hi> of <hi>all.</hi> The Spirit of the Lord dwels in the perfect man; and where the <hi>Spirit</hi> is and abides, <hi>all his Graces</hi> are <hi>with him.</hi> This is plainly intimated, John 1. 16. <hi>Of his fulneſs we all have received and grace for grace.</hi> There are ſeveral Interpretations of theſe Words, but the trueſt is this: Of <hi>Chriſt's fulneſs</hi> all <hi>ſincere believers</hi> have <hi>received</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Grace anſwerable to every grace that is in Chriſt himſelf;</hi> as the Child receives Limb for Limb from the Parent. How truly Rich and Happy is he who has <hi>no Grace wanting!</hi> and what a ſatisfaction is it to perceive plainly in himſelf, that <hi>every Grace is growing!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. The perfect man <hi>priſes all the promiſes of the New Covenant,</hi> and eſteems himſelf highly favoured in being Heir unto them all. Hypocritical Profeſſors, and Wicked Men, may put a value upon <hi>ſome promiſes;</hi> as when the Lord promiſes <hi>to bleſs in the City, and in the Field,</hi> to bleſs in <hi>the fruit of the Body, and of the Cattle, and of the Ground;</hi> to bleſs <hi>in the Basket, and in the Store,</hi> Deut. 28. 3, 4, 5. when he promiſes <hi>length of days, and long life, and that peace ſhall be added,</hi> Prov. 3. 2. Nay one that is ungodly, deſigning to die the death of the Righteous, may put a value upon the promiſes of <hi>deliverance from the wrath to come,</hi> and from <hi>eternal condemnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:34189:9"/>
            <p> But the perfect man, though he ſets an eſtimate upon any Bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which God has promiſed, and values Temporal Mercies, and Salvation from the Vengeance of eternal Fire: Yet there are alſo other kind of promiſes he gladly embraces, as the promiſe of an <hi>heart to know the Lord.</hi> Jer. 24. 7. <hi>I will give them an heart to know me, that I am the Lord, and they ſhall be my people, and I will be their God, for they ſhall return to me with their whole heart.</hi> That promiſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of <hi>an heart circumciſed to love God,</hi> is much valued and reſted on by the perfect man. Deut. 30. 6. <hi>The Lord thy God will circumciſe thy heart, and the heart of thy ſeed, to love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, that thou mayſt live.</hi> So is that promiſe, Ezek. 36. 25. <hi>Then will I ſprinkle clean water upon you, and ye ſhall be clean: from all your filthineſs and from all your idols I will cleanſe you.</hi> There is good reaſon that the promiſes of <hi>ſanctification</hi> ſhould be look'd upon as <hi>exceeding great and precious;</hi> for by theſe the perfect man is made <hi>a partaker of the divine nature, and eſcapes the corruption that is in the world through luſt,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 4.</p>
            <p>4. The perfect man hath <hi>a reſpect unto all God's commandments;</hi> he does not <hi>chuſe ſome,</hi> and <hi>paſs by others;</hi> but readily receives every precept. Pſal. 119. 6. <hi>Then ſhall I not be aſhamed when I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto all thy commandments.</hi> He looks upon every Law with an <hi>eye to the Authority</hi> of the <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> who has a <hi>right to rule</hi> him, and <hi>has power to ſave and deſtroy,</hi> John 4. 12. He looks upon the Law delivered on Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> as in <hi>force</hi> upon Mount <hi>Zion;</hi> and that <hi>by faith the law is eſtabliſhed,</hi> Rom. 3. 31. The Apoſtle's manner of Expreſſion carries in it a ſtrong motive to Obedience, 1 Theſſ. 4. 2. <hi>For ye know what commandments we gave you by the Lord Jeſus.</hi> Commands are given by his <hi>Authority,</hi> who <hi>is Lord of all;</hi> and Obedience is urged for his <hi>ſake,</hi> who himſelf has obeyed and ſuffered for us; and who is ſo ready to ſtrengthen us to obey, and to make what we do acceptable.</p>
            <p>The perfect man has his eye upon God and Chriſt, and cannot find in his Heart to caſt any Command of <hi>theirs</hi> behind his Back; that's his perpetual wiſh, that's his daily groan; <hi>Oh, that my ways were directed to keep thy Statutes! Oh, let me not wander from thy Commandments!</hi> Pſal. 119. 5, 10. Whereas the unſound Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor is not <hi>reconciled</hi> to <hi>every Command,</hi> nor indeed to <hi>any.</hi> Though his Obedience ſeem exact <hi>in many reſpects,</hi> yet <hi>offending in one point</hi> or other, he is guilty of violating <hi>the whole law,</hi> James 2. 10. His partial Obedience to the Commands, ſhews he is not <hi>ſincere</hi> in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34189:9"/> keeping <hi>any one</hi> of them. If <hi>any</hi> were kept upon a <hi>right ground,</hi> then <hi>every one</hi> of the Precepts would be kept upon the <hi>ſame ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. The perfect man <hi>keeps judgment and does righteouſneſs at all times,</hi> Pſal. 106. 3. He <hi>ſticks to the Lord's teſtimonies,</hi> and <hi>cleaves to the Lord himſelf</hi> with an unſhaken <hi>purpoſe of heart,</hi> even in times of great Apoſtacy and falling away: He will not leave the <hi>Ship of the Church,</hi> and put to <hi>ſhore</hi> when a ſtorm of Perſecution ariſes; 'tis better to be in the <hi>Veſſel</hi> where <hi>Chriſt</hi> is, though the Tempeſt be never ſo fierce and ſore, than <hi>truſt</hi> to a <hi>ſinful compliance</hi> with the men of the World. The perfect man's <hi>goodneſs</hi> is not <hi>like the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cloud,</hi> and the <hi>early Dew that goes away;</hi> but his Righteouſneſs is like a River.</p>
            <q>Labitur &amp; labetur in omne volubilis aevum.</q>
            <p>It holds on its courſe, and keeps running continually. He ſhews himſelf a <hi>Diſciple indeed</hi> by <hi>ſtill following</hi> his Maſter, and <hi>abiding in his word.</hi> John 8. 31. <hi>If ye continue in my word, then are ye my Diſciples indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6. The perfect man <hi>wiſhes and longs for a ſinleſs perfection.</hi> He really and earneſtly deſires to be as good as the Law would have him to be, every whit as Righteous as the Commandment requires; and when through Infirmity he breaks the Law, he is troubled. When the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>This we wiſh were your perfection,</hi> 2 Cor. 13. 9. Certainly his Charity began at home, and he <hi>wiſh'd his own perfection alſo.</hi> Theſe longings after unſpotted Purity, and to <hi>do the will of God on earth as it's done heaven,</hi> God obſerves, and is well pleaſed with. <hi>David</hi> did not build the Temple yet the Lord tells him he <hi>did well,</hi> in that it <hi>was in his heart</hi> to do it, 2 Chron. 6. 8. What was <hi>in heart</hi> to do, God reckons as <hi>done,</hi> and <hi>well done. Abraham</hi> did not actually Sacrifice his Son <hi>Iſaac,</hi> yet 'tis ſaid again and again that <hi>he offered him up,</hi> Heb. 11. 17. The Will for the Deed is accepted. The perfect man's <hi>Will,</hi> to be <hi>every way perfect,</hi> is very well taken. The more there is of a <hi>willing Mind,</hi> the more there is of a <hi>perfect Heart,</hi> 1 Chron. 28. 9.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place I am to ſhew <hi>wherein the perfection of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man lies;</hi> it lies in his <hi>being upright.</hi> I have deſcribed him in part already; but I ſhall farther give you the perfect man's Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, by ſetting him forth in his uprightneſs. This upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs does not only include <hi>Integrity,</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>Partiality,</hi> but it includes <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>Shew</hi> and <hi>Form;</hi> for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34189:10"/> Form wants the principal Dimenſion of Uprightneſs, which is <hi>Depth</hi> and <hi>Subſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall tell you in ſeveral particulars how the Scripture repreſents the upright man. Let Conſcience diligently mark the repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that you may diſcern whether you are upright or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The upright man <hi>acknowledges his ſin without allowed guile.</hi> He has no ſecret <hi>regard to any iniquity,</hi> ſo as to connive at it himſelf, ſo as to refuſe to acknowledge it to God. He freely and ingenuouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes to the Lord the worſt he knows of himſelf; and while he thus declares his Sin and diſlikes it, and himſelf for it, God covers it, and no longer imputes it to him, Pſal. 32. 1. 2. <hi>Bleſſed is he whoſe tranſgreſſion is forgiven, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe ſin is covered; bleſſed is the man to whom the Lord imputeth not iniquity, and in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile.</hi> Holy <hi>Job</hi> was cenſured by his Friends, as unſound in his Religion; but by many Arguments he vindicates his uprightneſs, <hi>Job</hi> 31. And among the reſt by <hi>this, ver.</hi> 33. That he had not <hi>covered his tranſgreſſion like</hi> Adam, <hi>by hiding his iniquity in his boſom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To excuſe Sin is inexcuſable; to defend Sin, How offenſive is it unto God! The upright man, in his Repentance, expoſes his Sin with its many Aggravations, till it appears as it is, <hi>out of meaſure ſinful;</hi> and concludes it, beyond meaſure, hateful. He is ready to ſpeak all he knows amiſs in himſelf; and that which he ſees not, he deſires may be detected, that he may be cleanſed from it: <hi>Search me, O God,</hi> ſays upright <hi>David, and ſee if there be any evil way in me,</hi> Pſal. 139. 23, 24. He was ſenſible of the wickedneſs of his Heart, and begs that God would create in him a <hi>clean one;</hi> and becauſe of the deceitfulneſs of his Heart, he prays that <hi>a right ſpirit might be renewed within him,</hi> Pſal. 51. 10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The upright man <hi>keeps himſelf from that ſin which in a ſpecial manner may be called</hi> his <hi>iniquity.</hi> He is ſo well acquainted with himſelf, as well to know, and much to obſerve what Sin or Sins do moſt eaſily beſet him; and he ſets the ſtrongeſt guard againſt thoſe Corruptions which he takes notice that naturally he is moſt ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly addicted to. Pſal. 18. 23. <hi>I was alſo upright before him, and I kept my ſelf from my iniquity.</hi> The upright man, who is naturally inclined to Covetouſneſs, watches and prays againſt the <hi>love of worldly wealth,</hi> as that which is <hi>the root of all evil.</hi> If his Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion inclines him to impure Luſts, he endeavours to prevent, or to quench theſe <hi>helliſh ſparks</hi> at <hi>firſt kindling,</hi> and to <hi>poſſeſs</hi> his <hi>heart,</hi> as well as <hi>veſſel, in ſanctification and honour.</hi> If he be of an haſty
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34189:10"/> Temper, what pains does he take to keep Paſſion under, and to be adorned with the <hi>meekneſs and gentleneſs of Chriſt!</hi> He is an upright man, who becauſe <hi>God has been ſo often diſpleaſed</hi> by it, can <hi>baniſh</hi> and <hi>hate</hi> that which was <hi>once a darling ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The upright man is <hi>a lover of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in ſincerity,</hi> Cant. 1. 4. <hi>Draw me, we will run after thee; we will be glad and rejoyce in thee, we will remember thy love more than wine; the upright love thee.</hi> The upright man <hi>is what he is</hi> by the Grace of Chriſt; that Grace made his Heart <hi>a good and honeſt one,</hi> which naturally was no better than the Hearts of others; and even now he <hi>cannot ſtand in Law,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his many Faults and Failings; were it not for <hi>Jeſus</hi> the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, his <hi>very uprightneſs</hi> could <hi>never be accepted.</hi> He has <hi>his all</hi> from Chriſt, he <hi>does all</hi> by <hi>his ſtrength;</hi> and what he does is <hi>through him acceptable to God:</hi> Well may his love to the Lord be ſtrong, to whom his Obligations are vaſtly great.</p>
            <p>His love to Chriſt is not in Word and Tongue only, but in Deed and in Truth. Love to Chriſt <hi>conſtrains him to live to him that died for him,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 14, 15. and rather than be ſeparated from Chriſt and from his love, he reſolves by the glorious Spirit's aid, to part with the moſt deſirable outward Comforts, and with Life it ſelf. It was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an <hi>uncorrupt and fervent love</hi> to the Lord Jeſus, which made the Apoſtle full of <hi>earneſt expectation and hope, that in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing he ſhould be aſhamed;</hi> and very willing that <hi>Chriſt ſhould be mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified in his body, whether it were by life or death,</hi> Phil. 1. 20.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The upright man <hi>walks before God in truth.</hi> He <hi>ſets himſelf before God,</hi> unto whoſe <hi>pure and piercing eye</hi> the <hi>inmoſt ſecrets</hi> of his Heart are <hi>open and naked;</hi> and he is ſenſible the Lord can <hi>take no pleaſure</hi> in him without <hi>ſincerity.</hi> 1 Chron. 29. 17. <hi>I know, O my God, that thou trieſt the heart, and haſt pleaſure in uprightneſs.</hi> The upright man <hi>ſets God before himſelf</hi> alſo. Pſal. 16. 8. <hi>I have ſet the Lord always before me; becauſe he is at my right hand, I ſhall not be moved.</hi> The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>approve</hi> himſelf to God, who always <hi>obſerved</hi> him; and he <hi>ſtays himſelf</hi> on <hi>God's everlaſting arm and ſtrength,</hi> that he might be upheld againſt all Temptation and Oppoſition, and be kept immoveable in Well-doing.</p>
            <p>Upright <hi>Hezekiah</hi> walked <hi>before God in truth and with a perfect heart, and did that which was good in his ſight,</hi> Iſa. 38. 3. His <hi>heart was</hi> in what he <hi>did,</hi> and he had the Heart-ſearcher's Approbation, and his Conſcience giving a Teſtimony for him; he <hi>has confidence towards God.</hi> An upright man may be influenced by the <hi>fear of puniſhment.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:34189:11"/> They were the <hi>Friends</hi> of Chriſt, to whom he ſpeaks thus, <hi>Be not afraid of them that kill the body, and after that have no more that they can do; but I will forewarn you whom you ſhall fear; fear him which after he hath killed, hath power to caſt into hell. Yea, I ſay unto you, fear him.</hi> The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> alſo thus expreſſes himſelf, <hi>My fleſh trembleth for fear of thee, and I am afraid of thy judgements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though fear has an influence, 'tis not the only inducement to walk with God. He that is upright knows that <hi>love</hi> is the <hi>great thing</hi> which God commands; and love hinders any <hi>other command</hi> from being accounted <hi>grievous.</hi> A man has a great evidence of up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs, when <hi>love is predominant</hi> in him, when he is <hi>byaſſed by love to God,</hi> to do theſe things that are pleaſing in his eyes; and he is overcome with a <hi>ſenſe</hi> of <hi>God's loving-kindneſs to him,</hi> and is <hi>truly his ſervant,</hi> Pſal. 26. 3. <hi>Thy loving-kindneſs is before my eyes, and I have walked in thy truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The upright man <hi>holds faſt his integrity.</hi> When Mammon and Satan combine to rob him of this Jewel, yet neither fair means nor foul can make him part with it. The <hi>reproaches</hi> of <hi>Job</hi>'s <hi>Friends</hi> did enter, and go deep into him; but <hi>a reproaching Conſcience</hi> would have been a thouſand times worſe: Therefore though he ceaſed to be <hi>Job the wealthy, Job</hi> the <hi>greateſt of all the men in the Faſt;</hi> yet he remained <hi>Job the upright ſtill,</hi> Job 27. 5, 6. <hi>Till I die I will not remove my inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity,</hi> neither the thing it ſelf, nor the evidence of it from me. <hi>My righteouſneſs I hold faſt, and will not let it go; my heart ſhall not reproach me ſo long as I live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Providences of God may ſometimes be dark and cloudy, and his Hand very heavy upon his upright ones; ſo that <hi>themſelves</hi> and <hi>others</hi> may be <hi>amazed</hi> at thoſe <hi>Trials</hi> which their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Patience</hi> may be put upon: Yet true Gold will endure the hotteſt Furnace, and loſe nothing of its Weight and Worth. However the Lord deals with them, the upright have reaſon to conclude the <hi>immutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of his love,</hi> and that his <hi>faithfulneſs never fails.</hi> Job 17. 8, 9. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright men ſhall be aſtonied at this, and the innocent ſhall ſtir up himſelf againſt the hypocrite. The righteous alſo ſhall hold on his way, and he that hath clean hands ſhall be ſtronger and ſtronger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if it be ask'd how the upright man comes to be thus <hi>tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of his ſincerity?</hi> I anſwer, 'Tis not only becauſe of the <hi>delight</hi> and <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> he <hi>finds</hi> in <hi>reflecting</hi> upon it; but alſo, and that chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe God's <hi>right hand upholds him,</hi> God <hi>fixes his heart,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news a <hi>ſtable and a conſtant ſpirit in him;</hi> it's God who keeps holy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34189:11"/> Inclinations and religious Purpoſes alive, and firm, and ſtrong in him. This is acknowledged by <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 41. 12. <hi>As for me, thou upheldeſt me in my integrity, and ſetteſt me before thy face for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third place it follows, What the perfect and upright man is <hi>worthy of.</hi>
            </p>
            <l>He is worthy to be <hi>marked.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>He is worthy to be <hi>beheld.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>Firſt, He is worthy to be <hi>marked.</hi> Mark <hi>the perfect man,</hi> ſaith the Text: And marked he ſhould be; and that both</p>
            <l>For <hi>conviction,</hi> and alſo</l>
            <l>For <hi>imitation.</hi>
            </l>
            <p n="1">1. The perfect and upright man is to be marked for <hi>conviction.</hi> As the Saints ſhall <hi>judge the World</hi> at laſt, ſo they are a <hi>conviction to the World</hi> at preſent. The wicked think <hi>it ſtrange</hi> that believers <hi>run not out with them to the ſame exceſs of riot;</hi> and their Tongues <hi>ſpeak evil of them,</hi> 1 Pet. 4. 4. But their Conſciences at the ſame time may fly in their own Faces, and tell them plainly that thoſe whom they ſpeak ill of, are much wiſer and better than themſelves. An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary Converſation is a very convincing thing, it <hi>ſtops</hi> the <hi>mouths</hi> of ignorant and evil Speakers. 1 Pet. 2. 15. <hi>For ſo is the will of God, that with well doing ye may put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men.</hi> It fills <hi>the faces of ſuch with ſhame;</hi> they being convinced that <hi>accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are falſe,</hi> when <hi>conſciences and converſations are good,</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 16. <hi>Having a good conſcience, that whereas they ſpeak evil of you as of evil doers, they may be aſhamed who falſly accuſe your good converſation in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the World did but mark the perfect man, it might prevent that <hi>woe</hi> from falling upon them which is denounced againſt them, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of offences</hi> which they are apt to take at Religion, as if <hi>it ſelf</hi> were but <hi>an imaginary thing,</hi> and all that profeſs it <hi>were Diſſemblers.</hi> And if <hi>looſe</hi> and <hi>carnal Profeſſors</hi> would but mark them whoſe <hi>exact and circumſpect walking</hi> does ſhew them to be <hi>ſincere,</hi> and <hi>Saints indeed;</hi> it might <hi>ſtartle their Conſciences</hi> and make them <hi>very unquiet,</hi> becauſe they are ſo <hi>very unlike thoſe,</hi> who in their manner of living, do <hi>ſhew forth the power of godlineſs;</hi> their Conſciences might call them <hi>vain men,</hi> their <hi>faith a dead faith,</hi> their profeſſion an empty and <hi>vain ſhew;</hi> Jam. 2. 20. <hi>But wilt thou know, O vain man, that faith without works is dead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:34189:12"/> 2. The perfect man is to be marked for <hi>imitation.</hi> That excellent Company of Faithful ones, mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a cloud of Witneſſes,</hi> Heb. 12. 1. here ſeems to be an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion to the <hi>cloud in the Wilderneſs</hi> which <hi>directed</hi> the Children of <hi>Iſrael to the land of Canaan.</hi> Perfect men are Clouds, their <hi>dark ſide,</hi> their <hi>faults and failings,</hi> if we obſerve any in them, it muſt be our care to <hi>eſchew</hi> them. But their <hi>bright ſide</hi> may be of great uſe for our <hi>direction and encouragement.</hi> When we obſerve how <hi>holy, heavenly,</hi> full of <hi>love to God and goodneſs,</hi> and <hi>diligent in the Lord's</hi> work <hi>others</hi> have been; we ſhould <hi>ſhew the ſame grace and diligence, to the full aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of hope, to the end. We ſhould by no</hi> means be <hi>ſlothful, but followers of them, who through faith and patience inherit the promiſes.</hi> Heb 6. 11. 12.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Lord himſelf</hi> indeed is incomparably the <hi>beſt Pattern;</hi> Sin ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver found any place in him. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 22. <hi>Who did no ſin, neither was guile ſound in his mouth.</hi> Never in the leaſt faulty, <hi>either in word or deed:</hi> Yet perfect and upright men are fair Copies for others to write after. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 17, 20. <hi>Brethren, be ye followers together of me, and mark them which walk ſo as ye have us for an example; for our converſation is in heaven.</hi> And Chap 4. 9. He ſays not only <hi>thoſe things which ye have heard,</hi> but what ye have <hi>ſeen in me, do, and the God of peace ſhall be with you.</hi> All would be better, if the beſt were but more imitated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As the perfect and upright man is to be <hi>marked;</hi> ſo he is worthy to be <hi>beheld;</hi> the Text ſays, <hi>Behold the upright.</hi> The <hi>Pſalmiſt beheld the tranſgreſſors, and was grieved:</hi> Upright men may be beheld with joy and pleaſure; though grief may well be raiſed, when by death they are ſnatched away. Now that the Upright man may be <hi>beheld</hi> to good purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Behold him <hi>in his uſefulneſs:</hi> Though the perverſe and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced World does think the Upright man <hi>not fit to live</hi> in it; yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the <hi>world is not worthy of him;</hi> and is very <hi>much beholding</hi> to him. When the world which lives in wickedneſs, and grows more and more wicked, is haſtening its own Judgment and Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the ſake of the Upright ones that are therein, 'tis ſpared. Though there was ſuch an abominable Crew of Wicked men in <hi>Sodom,</hi> which were <hi>ſinners before the Lord exceedingly;</hi> yet <hi>Sodom</hi> had ſtood undeſtroyed by Fire and Brimſtone, if <hi>ten righteous perſons</hi> had been found therein, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 32. when <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid, <hi>Oh let not my Lord be angry, and I will ſpeak but this once; peradventure ten</hi> righteous ones <hi>ſhall be found there; and he ſaid, I will not deſtroy it for ten ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:34189:12"/>
            <p> Nay, <hi>One Moſes</hi> ſtood in the Breach, when the Sins of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had opened a <hi>wide Gap</hi> for the Wrath of God to break in upon them, Pſalm 106. 23. <hi>Therefore he ſaid, he would deſtroy them, had not Moſes his choſen ſtood before him in the breach, to turn away his wrath, leſt he ſhould deſtroy them.</hi> However Infidels and ungodl ones may prate maliciouſly, the <hi>Puritans of a Nation</hi> are very much the ſecurity of it. Job 22. 30. <hi>He ſhall deliver the Iſland of the innocent;</hi> or it may be tranſlated, <hi>The Innocent ſhall deliver the Iſland;</hi> and <hi>it is delivered by the pureneſs of thy hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Behold the <hi>Grace of God in the upright Man, which makes him thus uſeful.</hi> Both the <hi>eſſe</hi> and the <hi>operati</hi> of the new Creature is from Divine Grace; by Grace the upright man <hi>is what he is,</hi> and by the ſame Grace he <hi>does what he does.</hi> Who ever <hi>laboured ſo abundantly</hi> as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul?</hi> Whoſe Labours were more ſucceeded to the <hi>Glory of God,</hi> to the <hi>Church's,</hi> and the <hi>World's benefit,</hi> than <hi>his were?</hi> Yet he aſcribes nothing to himſelf, but gives unto <hi>Grace</hi> all the <hi>Glory.</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 10. <hi>I laboured more abundantly than they all, yet not I, but the grace of God which was with me.</hi> When you behold the upright man, you muſt <hi>ſee God in him, and with him of a truth.</hi> Men are not to <hi>glory,</hi> or to be <hi>gloried in; but he that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. 31.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Behold the upright man, ſo as to <hi>deſire and hope that the ſame Grace which made him upright, may make you ſo.</hi> Upright ones were not ſuch by their <hi>firſt Birth,</hi> but by their <hi>ſecond.</hi> The Apoſtle readily makes this acknowledgment, Eph. 2. 3. <hi>Among whom alſo we all had our converſation in times paſt in the luſts of our fleſh, fulfilling the deſires of the fleſh, and of the mind, and were by nature the children of wrath, even as others.</hi> Therefore concerning ſincere Saints, it muſt be ſaid, That <hi>they are born not of blood, nor of the will of the fleſh, nor of the will of man, but of God,</hi> John 1. 13. And <hi>that</hi> God <hi>who of his own will begat them with the word of truth,</hi> can eaſily alſo <hi>regenerate you</hi> by the the ſame means, and by his own powerful Grace, make <hi>more veſſels of honour</hi> (all upright ones are ſuch) out of the <hi>Maſs of corrupted Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the fourth place I am to ſhew, <hi>What of this perfect and upright Man</hi> our <hi>eye in a ſpecial manner</hi> ſhould be <hi>upon,</hi> and that is <hi>his end.</hi> To look to the <hi>end of Perſons and Things,</hi> and likewiſe thoſe things that are <hi>endleſs,</hi> is a great piece of Wiſdom. By the upright man's <hi>End</hi> we are to underſtand his <hi>Diſſolution and Death,</hi> whereby he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34189:13"/> ceaſes to be any longer in this World. Not that Death does make an end of him; the Soul is <hi>redeemed from the power of the grave, for God doth receives it,</hi> Pſalm 49. 15. and the Body ſhall not <hi>always</hi> be the <hi>Graves priſoner;</hi> but the Union between theſe two conſtituent parts by Death is diſſolved. Now there are ſeveral things of the perfect and upright man which Death does <hi>put an end</hi> unto.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Death puts an end to the upright man's <hi>Labour.</hi> Labour <hi>in the Lord,</hi> and <hi>for the Lord,</hi> is the upright man's buſineſs in this World. He has no time to waſte, neither is he allowed to be idle. <hi>Working hard</hi> and <hi>living,</hi> muſt run <hi>parallel:</hi> Nay, with alluſion to what <hi>Caeſar</hi> once ſaid, we may affirm, <hi>Neceſſe eſt laborare, non eſt neceſſe vivere.</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring is more neceſſary than living. While the upright man lives, he muſt be <hi>ſtedfaſt, unmoveable, always abounding</hi> in the doing of good. But when Death comes, it ſignifies to him that his Work is at an end. Rev. 14. 13. <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, from henceforth, yea, ſaith the ſpirit, that they may reſt from their labours, and their works do follow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Death puts an end to the upright man's <hi>Sorrows;</hi> here in this World, he is in his <hi>Minority,</hi> and is under the Diſcipline of the <hi>Rod;</hi> after Death he will not need it. His gracious Father in great faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, conſults the upright man's neceſſity; and if <hi>need be, he is in heavineſs through manifold temptations,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 6. and yet ſtill there is a mixture of mercy with the greateſt ſeverity; the <hi>Son of God</hi> is with the ſincere Saint in <hi>every Furnace,</hi> and his <hi>Preſence</hi> makes the Furnace both <hi>tolerable</hi> and <hi>purifying:</hi> Under the heavieſt Burthens; <hi>everlaſting Arms</hi> ſhall <hi>ſuſtain</hi> him, and well may he be <hi>comforted</hi> with the thoughts of <hi>everlaſting Love.</hi> But the end of his days puts a full period to his Troubles and Sorrows; his Heart ſhall ake, his Tongue complain, his Eyes ſhall weep no more; Rev. 7. 17. <hi>The Lamb which is in the midſt of the Throne ſhall feed them, and ſhall lead them unto li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving fountains of waters, and God ſhall wipe away all tears from their eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Death puts an end to the upright man's <hi>Conflicts.</hi> His Life is a warfare, he fights every ſtep of his way to Heaven; his Enemies are much ſtronger than he; called <hi>Principalities and Powers</hi> whom he wrrſtles with; but he is furniſhed with the <hi>whole Armour of God,</hi> and his ſtrength lies in Chriſt the <hi>Captain of his Salvation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Chriſt has encountred theſe Enemies in his own Perſon, tried their force, and triumphed over them; and as he has his Followers at command, ſo he can <hi>command Salvation</hi> for them. Satan is a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34189:13"/> troubleſome and unwearied Adverſary; and when the upright man is <hi>juſt going;</hi> this Enemy may give him a <hi>blow at parting.</hi> He uſually endeavours to make a <hi>Saint's Death-bed uneaſy and uncomfortable;</hi> and ſometimes he ſtrives to lift up the perfect man with <hi>Spiritual Pride;</hi> As the famous <hi>Knox</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> was tempted to an <hi>high Opinion of himſelf</hi> when he was near expiring, becauſe he had been ſo faithful in his miniſtry; but he aſcribed all that he <hi>was</hi> and <hi>did</hi> unto the <hi>Grace of God;</hi> and Satan was quite ſoiled. But when Death comes, it removes the upright man out of Satan's reach. He is made <hi>more than a conqueror through Chriſt who has loved him;</hi> having overcome, he <hi>ſits down in that throne</hi> with his bleſſed Lord himſelf, where he ſhall never be moleſted more with any of the Enemies of his Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Death puts end to the upright man's <hi>natural Life.</hi> Tho his Life on Earth is far from being a <hi>noxious</hi> and <hi>hurtful Vapour;</hi> yet 'tis a <hi>vapour which appeareth for a little time, and then vaniſheth away,</hi> Jam. 4. 14. The Bodies of the Juſt muſt be brought down into the Grave, as well as the Bodies of others; that mankind, and beſt of men may have a <hi>ſenſible Document</hi> how hateful Sin is to God; upon <hi>all that have ſinned death paſſes,</hi> Rom. 5. 12. Tho the Bodies of the Saints are <hi>Members of Chriſt,</hi> and Inſtruments of <hi>Righteouſneſs to Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and the <hi>Temples of the Holy Ghoſt</hi> himſelf, yet theſe Temples muſt be demoliſhed and caſt to the ground, and for a while turned under it; and after they have been ſo long impriſoned in the Grave, how glorious will be the ſtrength and love of Chriſt their Lord and Head, in reſcuing his Members all of them from under Death's Dominion, and in totally <hi>aboliſhing Death</hi> it ſelf! and how will the <hi>power of the Spirit</hi> be manifeſted in <hi>rearing up his Temples</hi> out of the <hi>Duſt,</hi> and in making them ſo <hi>tranſcendently glorious,</hi> and likewiſe ſo <hi>firm and durable,</hi> that they ſhall <hi>ſtand and abide unto eternity!</hi> Rom. 8. 11. <hi>If the ſpirit of him that raiſed up Chriſt from the dead dwell in you; he that raiſed up Chriſt from the dead, ſhall alſo quicken your mortal bodies, by his ſpirit that dwelleth in you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Death puts an end to <hi>all that Corruption which remains in the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Man.</hi> Sin was the Parent of Death, and at Death ſin it ſelf is totally deſtroyed. The mortal and corruptible Body of the Saint ſhall at length put on Incorruption and Immortality; but the body of Sin is <hi>annihilated,</hi> and ſhall <hi>be no more;</hi> he ſhall never complain of <hi>any evil preſent</hi> with him, nor be <hi>troubled</hi> with any the <hi>leaſt luſtings of the fleſh againſt the Spirit.</hi> How <hi>contrary</hi> and <hi>offenſive</hi> to the <hi>new Nature,</hi> were
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34189:14"/> the remainders of the <hi>old Man which is corrupt according to deceitful luſts!</hi> But at Death the upright man when he puts off his earthly Tabernacle, does <hi>quite put off the old Man;</hi> not the leaſt Member of that Body can remain unmortified; and in what <hi>glorious perfection</hi> does he <hi>put on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt!</hi> He is <hi>perfecting Holineſs</hi> while he lives, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 1. which intimates that at Death his Work and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to cleanſe himſelf will be at an end, and Holineſs will be <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</hi> And how <hi>beautiful and glorious</hi> will his <hi>ſeparate Soul</hi> be in its <hi>perfected and unſpotted Purity!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the fifth place, The end of the perfect and upright man is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable as well as himſelf, for <hi>his end is Peace.</hi> The Scripture is true concerning him, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7. 1. <hi>The day of his death is better than the day of his birth.</hi> He was born into a <hi>wicked</hi> and a <hi>wretched World,</hi> but Death ſends him to an <hi>everlaſting Habitation</hi> of Bliſs, and Life, and Glory. His <hi>dying day</hi> may well be the <hi>joyfulleſt day that ever he lived,</hi> becauſe the <hi>laſt moment</hi> of his time is his <hi>entrance</hi> into a <hi>bleſſed Eternity.</hi> He is indeed a <hi>Son of Peace,</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> ſhould not <hi>diſturb it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The perfect and upright man dies in <hi>peace with God.</hi> He is <hi>reconciled to God by the death of his Son:</hi> How ſure is Salvation upon ſuch a Reconciliation! The Enmity between God and him, <hi>being ſlain by the Croſs of Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 2. 16. the <hi>Value and Virtue</hi> of Chriſt's <hi>Crucifixion</hi> muſt needs make <hi>Peace that is laſting.</hi> The middle Wall of Partition that is thrown down, ſhall never be reared up again. The upright man's Sins are all removed from him, <hi>as far as the Eaſt is from the Weſt,</hi> Pſalm 103. 12. and he may as well imagine the <hi>two Poles</hi> that are ſo far diſtant ſhould meet together, as fear that any of his Sins which <hi>are not imputed</hi> to him, ſhould <hi>again be laid unto his charge.</hi> Rom. 8. 33. <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect? it is God that juſtifieth: who is he that condemneth? it is Chriſt that died.</hi> Neither at <hi>Death</hi> nor <hi>Judgment</hi> ſhall any of their <hi>Sins be found againſt</hi> them that are upright. A Covenant of Peace is made with them more firm than the ſtrongeſt Hills and Mountains. Iſaiah 54. 10. <hi>The mountains ſhall depart, and the hills be removed, but my kindneſs ſhall not depart from thee, nor the covenant of my peace be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, ſaith the Lord that hath mercy upon thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The perfect and upright man dieth in <hi>peace with others.</hi> If <hi>all things are to be done with charity,</hi> 1 Cor. 16. 14 then <hi>dying</hi> muſt be <hi>in Charity</hi> likewiſe. How can he <hi>dye</hi> in the <hi>love of God,</hi> whoſe heart
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34189:14"/> is full of <hi>malice</hi> and <hi>hatred</hi> to his <hi>Brother?</hi> I remember what that bleſſed <hi>Martyr, Bradford,</hi> ſaid at his Death, <hi>I ask all the World for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs, and I forgive all the World;</hi> there was a great deal of <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> in this <hi>Expreſſion.</hi> The World had dealt very hardly with him, and was ſo furious as to <hi>burn him with Fire,</hi> yet he <hi>forgave the Injury.</hi> Thus the <hi>Protomartyr Stephen</hi> of old, from his heart for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave his Perſecutors; and his <hi>laſt Prayer</hi> was for <hi>them,</hi> that God would not lay their <hi>Sin</hi> and blood-guiltineſs to <hi>their charge, Acts</hi> 7. 60. When the heart is emptied of <hi>Wrath</hi> and <hi>Bitterneſs,</hi> and <hi>deſire of Revenge,</hi> whatever <hi>Injuries</hi> have been <hi>received;</hi> when peace has been purſued, and there has been an <hi>univerſal Love</hi> to <hi>all Saints;</hi> and in <hi>Obedience</hi> to <hi>Chriſt's Command</hi> it has been extended even to <hi>deſpightful Enemies;</hi> here is a comfortable evidence of Peace with God, and of an intereſt in his Love. <hi>Forgive,</hi> ſays Chriſt, and <hi>you</hi> your ſelves <hi>ſhall be forgiven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The perfect and upright Man when he comes to dye, has rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and good ground to have <hi>peace within himſelf.</hi> I dare not affirm, That every good Man concludes his Days with <hi>this Peace.</hi> The <hi>Letters</hi> of Mr. <hi>Paul Bains</hi> diſcover a <hi>great meaſure</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Holineſs,</hi> and an <hi>excellent Spirit</hi> in him; yet he profeſſes himſelf a <hi>great Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> to the <hi>Sweetneſs</hi> of Religion, and the <hi>Joys</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt; that diſconſolate humour of Melancholly poſſibly might be one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it. Nay, when he came to dye, his Death-bed was uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, and ſadneſs remained upon his Spirit till he <hi>entred into the Joy of his Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet I am ſure there is ſufficient ground for <hi>peace within</hi> the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Man. For Chriſt died that <hi>Death</hi> might be <hi>unſtung;</hi> and that Believers might <hi>not</hi> be <hi>terrified</hi> at it, but <hi>triumph</hi> over it. <hi>Through Death he deſtroyed the Devil,</hi> as he had the <hi>Power of Death,</hi> that is, to make <hi>Death terrible,</hi> and conſequently <hi>deliver them, who through the fear of death were all their life-time ſubject to bondage,</hi> Heb. 2. 14, 15. What a moſt deſirable way of dying is this, when Conſcience has <hi>great Peace,</hi> being <hi>purged</hi> and healed by the <hi>Blood of Chriſt!</hi> When the God of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Peace, ſpeaks Peace</hi> to the <hi>departing Soul</hi> by his <hi>comforting Spirit!</hi> And a Saint can ſay with <hi>righteous Simeon</hi> of old, Luke 1. 29, 30. <hi>Lord, now letteſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace, for my eyes have ſeen thy ſalvation!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. When the perfect and upright man dies, what <hi>a glorious and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Peace does he enter into in the other World.</hi> In thoſe <hi>bleſſed Regions</hi> unto which he goes, there is <hi>Light without Darkneſs,</hi> there is <hi>Love</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34189:15"/> the <hi>leaſt Diſcord,</hi> there is <hi>Joy</hi> without any <hi>Sorrow,</hi> and <hi>ſecure Poſſeſſion</hi> without any <hi>Diſturbance,</hi> or <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>Deprivation.</hi> The <hi>gulph</hi> that is <hi>fixed,</hi> Luke 16. 26. as it for ever baniſhes <hi>Hope</hi> out of <hi>Hell,</hi> ſo it leaves not the <hi>leaſt room</hi> for <hi>Fear</hi> in <hi>Heaven.</hi> It is much to be lamented, that Saints at this day diſcover <hi>no more of love,</hi> and of a <hi>peaceable Temper,</hi> but when they are all come to the <hi>ſame Heaven,</hi> God who is <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> will be <hi>all in all,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 28. and <hi>they all</hi> will be perfectly <hi>One in Him!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to the <hi>Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I ſhall ſpeak,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Concerning the <hi>perfect and upright Man,</hi> who is lately taken from us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> A <hi>few words</hi> to <hi>you</hi> that <hi>ſurvive</hi> him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Concerning the <hi>Perſon deceaſed.</hi> And truly I ſpeak not only my <hi>Affection,</hi> but my <hi>Conſcience,</hi> when I ſay, <hi>I do believe there was not a Man upon Earth that better deſerved to be called a perfect Man, than our Mr.</hi> Edward Lawrence. A Man more free from all the <hi>tricks of fleſhly Wiſdom,</hi> more free from <hi>petty Revenges,</hi> and <hi>petty Deſigns</hi> againſt <hi>any Party;</hi> I confeſs I knew not any. Upright he was towards God, <hi>downright</hi> in his <hi>Dealings with Men.</hi> An <hi>even</hi> and <hi>well-ſpun Thread of Truth,</hi> and <hi>Honeſty,</hi> and <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> ran through the <hi>whole Courſe</hi> of his <hi>Converſation</hi> in the World.</p>
            <p>Several things more particularly <hi>worthy of our notice,</hi> I ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He had attained to <hi>a great ſtrength and perfection of Faith.</hi> As he ſaw <hi>the inviſible God,</hi> and his Faith was the <hi>ſubſtance of things hoped for,</hi> and he <hi>mainly minded the inviſible World;</hi> ſo he could truſt in God, for the <hi>things of this World,</hi> when <hi>Senſe</hi> being <hi>judge,</hi> there was no <hi>probability</hi> of ſupply. He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> had a <hi>numerous Family</hi> when he <hi>left his Living</hi> on the <hi>Black Bartholomew-day;</hi> and being asked how he hoped to be provided for? He anſwered, That the Sixth of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> ſhould maintain him By Faith he reſted on that promiſe, that <hi>all other things ſhall be added</hi> to them who <hi>firſt ſeek the Kingdom of God, and his Righteouſneſs.</hi> He ſaid, His <hi>Heavenly Father knew he needed theſe things;</hi> and he made no queſtion but what he needed, would be given him. There is, I am perſwaded, an <hi>extraordinary Reliſh</hi> in the <hi>Meat</hi> and <hi>Drink,</hi> when <hi>Faith ſpreads the Table,</hi> and <hi>fills the Cup</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:34189:15"/> every day, and <hi>Senſe</hi> cannot perceive a <hi>Day before-hand</hi> how <hi>this ſhould be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. How <hi>perfect a Work had Patience in him!</hi> He was conformed to his Head Chriſt, in being a <hi>Man of Sorrows,</hi> and <hi>acquainted with Grief.</hi> He was exerciſed with Affliction in his own Perſon, and with Domeſtick Troubles which went very near him; yet he <hi>juſtified God</hi> in all; he believed that <hi>Good</hi> would come out of the <hi>Evils</hi> he felt; no Burthen <hi>tired his Patience,</hi> for he knew how <hi>happy they are that endure.</hi> In <hi>all Chaſtizements</hi> he perceived the <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> of his <hi>Chaſtizer,</hi> and this made all ſtrokes <hi>tolerable.</hi> His ſick Fits, his Pains, his weariſome and wakeful Nights, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, never made him, that ever I could hear, or hear of, to break forth into <hi>Murmurings or Complaints unbecoming him;</hi> whatever he wanted, he ſtill <hi>poſſeſſed his Soul in Patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He was a Man of a <hi>moſt Publick Spirit, and of a Catholick Charity.</hi> He was troubled to ſee the <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Body of</hi> Chriſt <hi>divided;</hi> ſo <hi>little conſulting</hi> the <hi>honour of their Head,</hi> or <hi>their own Intereſt.</hi> He was <hi>ſtiffly</hi> for no <hi>Party,</hi> very <hi>moderate</hi> towards <hi>all.</hi> True Goodneſs he liked and loved where-ever he ſaw it, and tho he had ſuffered very much from ſome <hi>bot Men</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> yet he was not bitter in his Speeches againſt them; where-ever he perceived uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, an unblameable Converſation, and a deſign for God carried on, he did readily acknowledge it, and rejoiced in it.</p>
            <p>He was not in the <hi>Quarrels</hi> of this <hi>preſent Age;</hi> he <hi>loved</hi> and <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed after Peace as well as Holineſs,</hi> and ſhared in the <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> which is promiſed to the <hi>Peace-makers.</hi> He was troubled to ſee <hi>roots of Bitterneſs</hi> bringing forth ſuch <hi>bitter Fruits</hi> almoſt <hi>every where,</hi> and in <hi>every Party.</hi> And with ſuch <hi>meekneſs of Wiſdom,</hi> with ſuch <hi>calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>ſedateneſs</hi> of Spirit, he carried it towards Men of all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions; and his Words and Ways were ſo <hi>inoffenſive,</hi> that I never heard any one ſpeak ill of Mr. <hi>Edward Lawrence,</hi> but all that knew him were ready to acknowledg that he was a <hi>Man of eminent Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of a moſt peaceable Temper, and of a very great Integrity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as he loved <hi>all Saints</hi> as <hi>ſuch,</hi> by what <hi>Name ſoever diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> ſo he <hi>vexed his righteous Soul from day to day,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs, Infidelity,</hi> and <hi>Debaucheries</hi> of this <hi>wicked Age.</hi> In his <hi>laſt Sermon</hi> which was upon that Text, Iſaiah 29. 6. <hi>When thy judgments are in the earth, the inhabitants of the world-will learn righteouſneſs,</hi> with very great Zeal and warmth, he preſſed upon his Hearers the <hi>learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:34189:16"/> the <hi>loving,</hi> the <hi>practice</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> for the <hi>Nations ſake,</hi> and for <hi>their own Souls ſake,</hi> that it <hi>might be well</hi> with the <hi>one,</hi> and with the <hi>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. He was a man of <hi>great Miniſterial Accompliſhments.</hi> His worth was like the <hi>deep Rivers</hi> which run more <hi>ſilently,</hi> whereas the <hi>ſhallow Brooks</hi> do make the <hi>greater Noiſe.</hi> He was very <hi>able</hi> in <hi>Controverſial Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;</hi> his <hi>Judgment</hi> was <hi>ſound,</hi> his <hi>Arguments ſtrong,</hi> his <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Notions</hi> very <hi>clear;</hi> and having a <hi>clear Apprehenſion</hi> of <hi>Truths himſelf,</hi> he could make them <hi>very plain</hi> to <hi>others underſtandings;</hi> and in his arguings he was very free from Paſſion; and when he ſaw he was likely only to ſtir up the <hi>Paſſion</hi> of others, inſtead of <hi>rectifying their Judgments,</hi> he would be <hi>ſilent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his <hi>Preaching</hi> he was very <hi>ſolid</hi> and <hi>ſubſtantial;</hi> he had a <hi>great firmneſs in Memory</hi> which continued to the laſt. He prayed and preached with ſuch a Spirit, as did evidence much of the <hi>preſence of God</hi> with him. How did he <hi>ſpeak to God?</hi> as one that <hi>ſaw him juſt before him!</hi> And when he ſpake to man, he ſpake as the <hi>Oracle of God</hi> with greateſt ſeriouſneſs, and as about things of the higheſt and everlaſting Concernment. How firmly was he <hi>himſelf perſwaded</hi> of thoſe <hi>Truths</hi> he propounded to others? He <hi>taught</hi> the Commands of Chriſt, and <hi>himſelf obeyed</hi> them, and was great uſeful in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place I ſhall ſpeak a few Words to <hi>you that ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that both to <hi>his Relations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to <hi>Others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To his Relations I ſhall ſay theſe three things,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Take notice of his <hi>great Affection to you,</hi> and how this Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was <hi>ſpiritualized;</hi> he loved <hi>you,</hi> but eſpecially <hi>your Souls,</hi> the <hi>moſt precious part</hi> of you; he was full of care that it might be well with you for ever, and was faithful in reproving, as the World can witneſs, when he ſaw occaſion; he uſed <hi>various Ways</hi> and <hi>Methods</hi> that his great end, <hi>your Happineſs,</hi> might be attained.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be ſure to <hi>follow his very good Example.</hi> What <hi>kind of Children</hi> ſhould the Children of <hi>ſuch a Father be!</hi> there would be a kind of <hi>monſtrouſneſs</hi> in being <hi>very groſly unlike</hi> to him! As to his <hi>youngeſt Son,</hi> who is a <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel,</hi> I <hi>heartily wiſh,</hi> tho it be an <hi>hard thing</hi> which I wiſh, <hi>that a double portion of his Fathers Spirit may be vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to him!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:34189:16"/> 3. Be encouraged by this, That your <hi>deceaſed Father has treaſured up a ſtock of Prayers for you;</hi> and you may expect a <hi>gracious return.</hi> If you <hi>give your ſelves to Prayers,</hi> God may anſwer his Supplications af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death in beſtowing Temporal, Spiritual, and Eternal Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits upon you.</p>
            <p>To <hi>others</hi> that hear me this day; I ſhall only give <hi>two words of Counſel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Think much of your later end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let it be your <hi>great care that your end may be peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Be all of you <hi>wiſe to conſider your later end.</hi> Death did ſet out againſt you as ſoon as you were born, and it makes ſtill <hi>nearer and nearer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches</hi> to you every day, and hour, and moment of your lives. <hi>Every ſtep</hi> you take is a <hi>ſtep</hi> towards the <hi>Grave.</hi> Every moment of your time which paſſes away brings you nearer to <hi>Eternity.</hi> God <hi>wiſhes you wiſe to conſider your later end;</hi> he will be much pleaſed to ſee you very earneſt with him to <hi>make you ſo;</hi> he is ready <hi>to teach you ſo to number your days, that you may apply your hearts unto wiſdom,</hi> Pſal. 90. 12. The ſerious thoughts of death will <hi>quicken</hi> you in your <hi>Duties,</hi> and break the <hi>force</hi> of <hi>Temptations:</hi> Think of the time when you muſt leave the World, that <hi>eagerneſs after the World</hi> may be <hi>aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> To how <hi>good purpoſe</hi> will you <hi>live,</hi> if with the Apoſtle <hi>you dye daily!</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 31.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let it be your <hi>care that your end may be peace.</hi> Believe in <hi>Jeſus</hi> the great <hi>Peace-maker</hi> between God and Man, that you may <hi>joy in him,</hi> becauſe <hi>by him you have received the atonement,</hi> Rom. 5. 11. Let your Faith be accompanied with <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> to the <hi>Laws of God.</hi> Pſal. 119. 165. <hi>Great peace have they that love thy law, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall offend them.</hi> Value the <hi>ineſtimable Jewel</hi> of a <hi>good Conſcience,</hi> and take heed of every thing that may defile and wound it. When the Apoſtle had the <hi>ſentence of death in himſelf;</hi> the <hi>teſtimony of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> that <hi>by the grace of God he had had his Converſation in the World in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity,</hi> did fill him with Peace and <hi>Joy,</hi> 2 Cor. 1. 9, 12. Never be <hi>weary of well-doing,</hi> that your Lord when he comes may <hi>find</hi> you <hi>ſo doing.</hi> 'Tis <hi>labour beſt beſtowed</hi> when you are <hi>diligent, that you may be found of him in peace without ſpot and blameleſs.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:34189:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Several Paſſages concerning Mr.</hi> Lawrence, <hi>out of</hi> Two Letters, <hi>which were ſent by</hi> Two Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, <hi>Eminent for</hi> Learning <hi>and</hi> Godlineſs, <hi>and both of them intimately acquainted with Him.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Firſt LETTER concerning Mr.</hi> Edward Lawrence.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Lawrence</hi> was admitted into <hi>Magdalene</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> in the Year 1645, and was Studious, a Promoter of ſerious Godlineſs among the young Scholars; and was ſo noted alſo for his Parts and Learning, that we would have made him a Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. But when he had taken his Degree of Batchellor of Arts, (ſome Years after, he took the Degree of Maſter of Arts) he, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome ways engaged, went into the Countrey, and began to preach (having been of a good Age when admitted, about 18 as I remember), and with much Acceptance. He took up with <hi>Baſchurch,</hi> a Vicaridge of about 60 <hi>l.</hi> a Year; where (though if he had ſought great things he might have been removed to a greater Place, conſidering the Love and Eſteem he had) he continued till <hi>Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomew</hi> 1662, and then left his Station and Subſiſtence, though he had a Wife and ſeven or eight Children, and no Eſtate; and oft uſed to ſay, He lived upon the ſixth of <hi>Matthew.</hi> About the Year 79, the <hi>Quakers</hi> riſing thereabout, he Diſputed with one of their Chief Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders, and ſhamefully baffled him in the Judgment of the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of the Hearers, and as appears by the Relation of it put out by the <hi>Quaker.</hi> He was dangerouſly ill, and upon his recovery put out his uſeful Book, <hi>Of Chriſt's Power over bodily Diſeaſes;</hi> which, though very good, I then told him was below moſt of his Sermons he uſually preached, of which I had heard many.</p>
               <p>How he was driven from <hi>Whitchurch,</hi> Mr. <hi>H.</hi> who was then in thoſe parts will, I ſuppoſe, punctually inform you; and for theſe laſt four or five and twenty Years, his Brethren in the City can give a good account of Him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:34189:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The Second LETTER.</head>
               <p>AFter Mr. <hi>Lawrence</hi> his remove by the <hi>Bartholomew Act</hi> from <hi>Baſchurch,</hi> where he had been many Years a Faithful Miniſter of the Goſpel of Chriſt, he ſojourn'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> while with his Wife and Children, at a Neighbouring Gentleman's Houſe within the Pariſh, who had a great Reſpect for him, and was very Kind to him; and he account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it a great Mercy that though the Law had ſilenced him, that he muſt not preach to his beloved Flock, yet he had his Abode amongſt them, and might be many ways uſeful to them. But when the <hi>Five Mile Act,</hi> ſo called, was to be put in Execution in <hi>March</hi> 66. he went to <hi>Tilſtock,</hi> a Village in <hi>Whitchurch</hi> Pariſh, in the ſame County, to ſojourn there, and there the Power of the Lord was with him greatly and made him Inſtrumental of much Good, both to the Town and in the Neighbourhood; the remembrance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is ſtill ſweet to many who are yet living. As he had opportunity he preach'd to them, both in Seaſon and out of Seaſon; and which was more, his Prudent, Pious Converſation was a continual Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. He had many Children and all with him, and no viſible Income wherewithal to buy them Bread, yet the Lord was graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pleaſed to make Proviſion both for him and them, ſo that they did not want: The ſixth of <hi>Matthew,</hi> as he was uſed to ſay, did maintain him. During his Abode there he buried a dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Daughter, named <hi>Sarah,</hi> which was a great Grief to him, for ſhe was grown up, and began to be uſeful; but it Comforted him that ſhe finiſhed Well; and God gave him two Sons inſtead of her, which repair'd the loſs. Another remove he had to <hi>Whitchurch</hi> Town, and while he was there in <hi>May</hi> 1670, when the ſevere Act againſt Conventicles commenc'd in the ſame Month; upon a Sabbath-day in the Afternoon he preach'd in a private Houſe only to four and the Family, where they were diſturbed by the Miniſter himſelf, Dr. <hi>M. F.</hi> in his own Perſon, with others attending him; and the Week following Convicted and Fined; the Miniſter 10 <hi>l.</hi> becauſe Poor; the Maſter of the Houſe 20 <hi>l.</hi> and two other of the Town 5 <hi>l.</hi> a piece; and one Woman 5 <hi>s.</hi> Upon each of which Diſtreſs was made ſhortly after with the greateſt Rigor. They judging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wrong'd, made their Appeal according to Law, and in <hi>March</hi> following had a Tryal at <hi>Salop,</hi> before Judge <hi>Twiſden.</hi> The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34189:18"/> againſt them was, That a Daughter of the Family (who was ſixteen Years of Age but a few Days before) coming home from <hi>Cheſter</hi> from an Uncle the had there, was one preſent, and being none of the Family of her Father made a fifth. The Caſe was argu'd by Council, and the Proſecutors made no other account but that the Jury would give their Verdict for the Juſtices, who were the Defendants, and lay treble Damages upon the Plantiffs, which were intended to be made very great to their utter undoing. But it pleaſed God, in whoſe Hands are the Hearts of all Men, without any Motion or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement of theirs to incline one of the Jurors to differ in the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict from the reſt, ſaying, He would rather dye than ſay the Girl was none of her Father's Family. This occaſioned their ſtay toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all Night; and in the Morning being accuſed of ſome words ſpoken by him in their heat of Arguing, to one of his Fellow-Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, he was ſeverely Rebuked and Fined 10 <hi>l.</hi> and the Cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to two Lawyers, who never made any Deciſion of it, ſo that each ſide ſat down with his own Loſs; and not long after ſuch of their Goods, as were taken from them they had again, but much demnified. 'Twas obſerved, That one of the Proſecuting Juſtices dying during the Proſecution, his Houſhold-Goods were Proclaimed in the Town to be Sold, and were Sold before Chapmen could be found that would buy the Diſtrained Goods. The Informer that told he ſaw the Perſons going into the Houſe, did afterwards beg his Bread from Door to Door. This Event occaſioned the remove of this Excellent Perſon out of his own Native Countrey, where he dwelt among his own People, to ſeek a Habitation elſewhere among Strangers; and to <hi>London</hi> he went, where God gave him Favour in the ſight of many who ſat down under his Miniſtry, and with whom he ended his Days.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Lately Printed,</head>
            <p>THe Cure of Diſtractions in attending upon God. In ſeveral Sermons from 1 Cor. 7. 35. <hi>That we may attend upon the Lord without diſtraction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Love of the World cured. In ſeveral Sermons preached upon 1 John 2. 15. <hi>Love not the world,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Both by <hi>Nathanael Vincent.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34189:18"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
